We've been making a guest list so far for the party.
Parti için misafir listesi yapıyorduk.
&gt;&gt; Wait, this is the guest list for the birthday party, right, Catherine?
Doğumgünü partisinden bahsediyorsun değil mi Catherine?
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
Evet.
&gt;&gt; I really hope I'm on this list.
Umarım listedeyim.
&gt;&gt; Well, we'll have to see about that.
Bakacağız artık.
&gt;&gt; Wow, I feel really small about that.
Gerçekten küçük düşmüş hissettim.
&gt;&gt; Well, speaking about small,
Küçük demişken
let's talk about the size of views on a screen.
ekrandaki görüntü boyutları hakkında konuşalım.
&gt;&gt; Oh, we've used the fixed written height, which is the dp, right?
Sabit yükseklik kullanmıştık değil mi, dp olan?
&gt;&gt; Yeah, the width and height.
Evet, genişlik ve yükseklik.
And we could also set, wrap content, with view.
Ayrıca içeriği sar (wrap_content) olarak ayarlayabiliriz.
&gt;&gt; Right, which is a strange way of saying that the view is going to
Ki bu görüntünün kendisini içeriğin etrafına sarmasının
wrap itself around the content.
garip bir şekilde söylenişidir.
So the content grows large,
Yani içerik büyürse,
the view grows large, the content is small and the view grows small.
görüntü de büyür, içerik küçükse görüntü de küçülür.
&gt;&gt; Yeah, and there's actually a third one which is called, match parent.
Evet ve aslında bir üçüncü şey daha var, adı da match parent.
That sounds like a dating website for single parents.
Kulağa yalnız anne babalar için randevu sitesiymiş gibi geliyor.
&gt;&gt; Not quite.
Pek sayılmaz.
Match parent means that the view will be As wide or as tall as the parent.
Match parent demek görüntü üst öğe kadar geniş veya uzun olur demek.
&gt;&gt; Oh, so that makes sense.
Mantıklı.
I am a view, I have a parent and my width and
Ben bir görüntüyüm, benim bir üst öğem var ve
height is going to be the same as my parent.
genişlik ve yüksekliğim de üst öğem ile aynı olacak.
Okay. &gt;&gt; Exactly, so that's to summarize,
- Tamam. - Aynen, yani özetlersek,
the different values that you can set for a size of a view is width.
bir görüntünün boyutu için ayarlayacağınız farklı değerler genişliktir.
Fixed dp for width and height.
Genişlik ve yükseklik için sabit dp.
&gt;&gt; Correct, you can also do wrap_content.
Doğru, ayrıca wrap_content de yapabilirsin.
And the next one we're going to try out is
Ve deneyeceğimiz diğer şey ise
&gt;&gt; match_parent.
match_parent.
Here are some examples of how setting different widths on the child views
LinearLayout'ta alt görüntüde farklı genişlik değerlerin son kullanıcı
in a linear layout can affect the final user interface.
arayüzünü nasıl etkileyebileceğine dair birkaç örnek verelim.
In this example we set each child view to have a fixed width of 200 dp.
Bu örnekte her alt görüntüyü sabit 200 dp değerine ayarlıyoruz.
If the content inside each view is greater than 200 DP
Eğer her görüntüdeki içerik 200 dp'den büyük ise
then you run risk of cutting some content off like this.
o zaman bunun gibi bazı içeriği kırmayı göze almalısınız.
In this example we set each child view to have a width a wrap content.
Bu örnekte, her alt görüntü genişliğini wrap_content olarak ayarlıyoruz.
Now all the content content is shown, but
Şimdi tüm içerik gösteriliyor fakat
the width of each view really varies based on what's inside each view.
her görüntünün genişliği içeriğine olana bağlı olarak değişiyor.
In this example, we set the width of each child view to be match parent.
Bu örnekte, her alt görüntü genişliğini match_parent olarak ayarlandı.
Now you see that the width of each child is as wide as the parent view group.
Gördüğünüz gibi, her alt öğenin genişliği üst görüntü grubu kadar oluyor.
Regardless of the content inside of it.
İçeriğine bağlı değil.
Now those same values can also be applied for the height of each view.
Bu aynı değerler her görüntü yüksekliği için de uygulanabilir.
In this example we set the height of this child text view to be 200 dp.
Bu örnekte bu alt görünümün yüksekliğini 200 dp olarak ayarladık.
If the content inside it is taller than that.
Eğer içeriği ondan uzunsa
Then you run the risk of cutting off some of the content.
o zaman içeriğin bir kısmının kırpılması riski bulunuyor.
In this example, we set the height of the child text view to be wrap content.
Bu örnekte, bu alt görünümün yüksekliğini wrap_content ayarladık.
That way all the content will be displayed on screen and
Böylece tüm içerik ekranda gösterilecek ve
nothing will be cut off because the size of the text view is dependent
hiçbir kırpma olmayacak çünkü metin görünümünün boyutu
on the content inside of it.
içeriğine bağlı olacak.
In this example, we set the height of the child text view to be match parent.
Bu örnekte, bu alt görünümün yüksekliğini match_parent ayarladık.
That way the child view is as tall as the parent itself,
Böylece alt görünüm üst öğe yüksekliğinde olacak ve
regardless of the content inside it.
içeriğine bağlı olmayacak.
Let's open the XML visualizer now and
Şimdi XML görüntüleyiciyi açalım ve
try to be more like our parents in the code.
kodlarken daha çok anne-babamız (parents) gibi olmaya çalışalım.
We're providing you a link to the XML visualizer with some starter code
Aşağıdaki notlarda başlangıç kodu ile birlikte
in the instructor notes below.
XML görüntüleyici linkini veriyoruz.
In this case, the LinearLayout is the root view
Bu durumda, LinearLayout bu layout'un kök görünümü
If we set match_parent for the width and height of this root view, and
Eğer kök görünüm genişlik ve yüksekliğini match_parent
we set this as the main layout of our app,
ve bunu uygulamanın ana layout'u ayarlarsak
then this linear layout will be as tall and wide as the device screen.
bu LinearLayout cihaz ekranı kadar uzun ve geniş olacak.
I can show you by setting the background of this linear layout
Bunu LinearLayout arkaplanını transparan olmayacak şekilde
to be a non-transparent color.
ayarlayarak gösterebilirim.
If I set a gray background color on this linear layout Then,
Bu LinearLayout arkaplanını gri yapsam,
you can see how the gray extends the full width and height of the device.
grinin cihaz genişlik ve yüksekliğini sardığını görebilirsiniz.
Now, what happens if I try to change the width or
Şimdi, bu TextView'ların genişlik veya
height of these text views to be match parent?
yüksekliğini match_parent olarak değiştirmeyi denersem ne olur?
To make it clear where the bounds of each view are,
Her bir görüntünün sınırlarını görmek için
I'm going to set a background color on each of the views.
her görüntü için bir arkaplan ayarlayacağım.
Now I'm going to change the height of this text view to be match parent.
Şimdi bu TextView yüksekliğini match_parent olarak değiştireceğim.
By the way, you spell it match_parent.
Bu arada, match altçizgi parent olarak yazın.
And now you see that this text view takes up the full height of the parent.
Gördüğünüz gibi bu TextView üst görünümün genişliğini aldı.
Unfortunately, it pushes everything else off the screen, so
Ne yazık ki, her şeyi ekranın dışına atar
we don't really want that.
yani bunu istemeyiz.
So let's change it back to wrap content.
O zaman onu tekrar wrap_content yapalım.
Okay.
Tamam.
So let's change the width now to be match parent and see what it does.
Şimdi genişliği match_parent yapalım ve ne yaptığını görelim.
Now the width of the TextView is as wide as the parent, which in turn,
Şimdi, TextView üst görüntü kadar geniş
If I change the other TextViews to also be match_parent
Eğer diğer TextView'ları da match_parent olarak değiştirirsem
You can see that it also starts to take up the full width of the parent.
onun da üst görünümün genişliğini aldığını görebilirsiniz.
I also want to point out one more thing.
Bir şeyi daha belirtmek istiyorum.
Every time you see an attribute that starts with layout underscore, like
Layout_ ile başlayan bir öznitelik görürseniz
layout height or layout width, these are actually view group layout parameters.
layout_height veya layout_width gibi, bunlar görüntüleme grubu layout parametreleridir.
These are used by the parent view group to determine the size and
Bunlar bu görüntülerin boyut ve konumunu belirlemek için
the position of these views.
üst görüntü grubu tarafından kullanılır.
Meanwhile, the other attributes like background, text size, and
Bu arada, arkaplan, metin boyutu ve metin gibi diğer öznitelikler
text are handled by the TextView in terms of styling its own view.
kendi görüntüsünü tasarım açısında TextView tarafından kontrol ediliyor.
But these view group layout parameters are handled by the parent.
Fakat bu grup layout parametreleri üst öğe tarafından halledilir.
Now it's your turn to try different width and height values.
Farklı genişlik ve yükseklik değerleri deneme sırası şimdi sizde.
For the link to the XML visualizer with some starter code,
Bazı başlangıç kodları ile XML görüntüleyici linki için
see the instructor notes below.
aşağıdaki ders notlarına bakın.
Try to change the width and height values of each TextView.
Her TextView için genişlik ve yükseklik değerlerini değiştirmeyi deneyin.
You can set a fixed dp value, wrap-content, or match_parent.
Sabit bir dp değeri belirleyebilir, wrap_content veya match_parent yapabilirsiniz.
Remember that for each view, the width and height values don't have to match.
Unutmayın ki, her görüntü için, genişlik ve yükseklik değerleri eşleşmek zorunda değil.
When you're done, check this box to continue.
Bitirdiğinizde, devam etmek için bu kutuyu işaretleyin.